Inventory of the John Marshall Papers 1771-1959
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, Family Members and Other Individuals, 1771-1916, n.d. (Box 1-5)
  - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1771-1835, n.d., 269 items. (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1790-1799., 39 items. (Box-folder 1:2-6)
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1797., 17 items. (Box-folder 1:3-5)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 5 July [17]97., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
          Is "extremely chagrined" at never receiving any mail from her; writes he will sail on the brig Grace for Amsterdam within the week to join General [Charles] Pinckney; discusses July 4th celebration of the Senators and Representatives.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 10 July [17]97., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
          Has received her letter of June 30; thanks Heaven for her improved health and warns her that "melancholy may inflict punishment" on her unborn child; mentions that Colonel [Robert] Gamble's wife would like to visit her; expects to sail by the beginning of next week at the latest and is upset at the delay; will finish his business and return as soon as possible; sends greetings to his children and mother-in-law; mentions the adjournment of Congress.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 11 July 1797., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
          Sends this letter by Mr. [Humphrey ?] Marshall; attended the play Romeo and Juliet last night, and compares Mrs. [Anne Bruton] Merry's"Juliet" to Richmond's Mrs. [Anne] West [Bignall's]; visited Mrs. [Susan] Heyward [sic] Hayward and gossips about her rumored upcoming marriage to [Henry] Baring; complains about delayed departure and wearies of dining out, as he begins "to require a frugal repast with good cool water"; wishes "that we were looking back on our separation instead of seeing it before us."
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 12 July [17]97., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
          Asks her to give a parcel of land deeds from [John?] Banks to Hobe, which can be found in his pine desk in his office, to the clerk of the General Court; is impatient to get on board ship and away; wishes he had spent another week in Richmond; with tomorrow's departure of the Republican, [Richard] Brent, the last of the Virginia Congressmen will have left the city; "my spirits sink at parting with them."
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 14 July [17]97., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
          Will board the Grace at New Castle on Sunday [July 18] and will hopefully arrive in Amsterdam by the end of August; should hear from him next in October; Mr. [John] Brown[his secretary] has just arrived on the last stage; received his son Tom's letter of July 6; dined yesterday at William Bingham's country seat on the Schuylkil; describes the table setting and Mrs. [Anne Willing] Bingham's dressing in the latest fashions; besides his Virginia relations, he most enjoys the company of Mr. [Robert] Morris' family.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, the bay of Delaware, to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 20 July [17]97., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
          Unfavorable winds have prevented them from reaching the open ocean; describes ship board accommodations, provisions, and companions, including John Brown, John G. Gamble, the Captain of the ship, Mr. Willis, and two Dutch gentleman; has sent a letter to Winchester, [Virginia] for his son, Tom; instructs her how to reach him [John Marshall] by letter.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 2 August to 29 August [17]97., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
          1200 or 1300 miles east of the Capes of Delaware, Marshall and the crew hailed a ship bound for America; has not been very seasick and has busied himself with reading; has arrived in Holland and sends news of his health and safety on the first American bound ship.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Amsterdam, to [Timothy Pickering], 2 September 1797., 4 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
          The captain of a British frigate of Admiral Duncan's fleet at the mouth of the Texel boarded their ship on August 29 but treated them extremely politely upon learning that a U.S. minister was on board; observed the Dutch fleet in the Texel ready to move on the British if negotiations at Lisle [sic] [Lille] failed; describes the internal politics of the French government: the Directory presses for war while the Council of Five Hundred desires peace, fearing the politicization of the French army; Lord Malmesberry [sic] [Malmesbury; William Harris] is at Lisle [sic] [Lille] negotiating for peace between Britain and France; Tayleran Perigord [sic] [Charles Maurice de Talleyran Perigord], the French Minister of foreign affairs, has sent orders to French parts to grant immediate passports to the American envoys.
        - John Marshall, the Hague, to [Timothy Pickering], 9 September 1797., 4 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
          Arrived at the Hague and met with General [Charles C.] Pinckney on September 3; has just heard from an express from the Dutch minister at Paris to the Committee of Foreign Affairs about the Directory with the aid of the army moving against royalist and right wing opponents in the Directory, the Council of Five Hundred and the Council of Elders; discusses the impact which this coup d'etat of 18 Fructidor should have upon foreign policy; the French government is now in the hands of those unfriendly to peace, and the moderates willing to judge the American case with fairness have been removed; received news of Mr. [Elbridge] Gerry's intended departure from Boston on July 23 and will await his arrival in Rotterdam for a week before they leave for Paris.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, the Hague, [Holland], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 9 September [17]97., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
          Reached the Hague on August 3 and is very much pleased with General [Charles C.] Pinckney; had intended to set out for Paris immediately, but Pinckney received news from [Elbridge] Gerry on August 5 that he will arrive at the end of August; is perplexed and mortified at the delay; describes the Hague and its social life; mentions lack of companions for Pinckney's wife and daughter; has enjoyed the theatre even though he does not understand the language, and applauds the performances of Madame [Louise Rosalie Lefebvre] de Gazon [sic] [DuGrazon]; the Directory's coup in Paris may abridge negotiations so as to occasion his return to America this fall, but he would resent such a circumstance even though he misses her immensely and is impatient to be with her again.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, the Hague, to [Timothy Pickering], 15 to 17 September 1797., 6 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
          The reports on the revolution in Paris have been confirmed; discusses violations of the French constitution, under the hand of the army, the very essence of a republic is destroyed, but "French liberty may survive the shock it has sustained;" "All power is now in the undivided possession of those who have directed against us those hostile measures of which we so justly complain;" will set out for Paris on Monday with or without [Elbridge] Gerry; contrary to previous reports, negotiations still continue at Lille; their route to Paris is prescribed on their permit, probably to prevent their passing through Lisle [sic]; [Philippe Antoine] and Merlin [de Douai] is chosen director to replace Barthelemey and [Nicholas] Francois de Neufchatil [sic] [Neufchateau] to replace Carnot; Mr. Noel, the minister of France at the Hague has just informed him that 1,500 people have been arrested at Lyons and that General [Andre] Massena is marching to Avignon to quell resistance there.
        - Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, J[ohn] Marshall, E[lbridge] Gerry, Paris, [France], to [Timothy Pickering], Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 27 November 1797., 5 pages. Pst of LS. (Box-folder 1:5)
          Includes a copy of the letter which the three submitted to the French minister of foreign affairs after waiting to be received for a month; they have yet to receive an answer to this November 11 letter, and the condemnation of American vessels continues; the following is written in a numeric cipher which is decoded in superscript: "Frequent and urgent attempts have been made to inveigle us again into negociation [sic] with persons not officially authorized, of which the obtaining of money is the basis...we have very little prospect of succeeding in our mission."
        - [John Marshall], Paris, to [Timothy Pickering, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 27 November 1797., 7 pages. Pst of AL. (Box-folder 1:5)
          Has enclosed an issue of the Conservative [sic] [ Conservateur(Paris)] as an example of the abuse of the U.S. by the French press; discusses the arrests of innocent American citizens in Paris, including the cases of [Jesse] Putnam, [James V.] Murray and his brother [George W. Murray]; discusses the situation of American merchant marines who, being forced ashore after their vessels were captured, have no choice but to become French privateers; "France resounds with the proposd [sic] invasion of England," but such talk may be designed merely to alarm Britain; discusses France's continental ambitions and Spain's situation; writes of the internal France political scene; encloses the November 7 issue of the Leyden gazette with news of [Emmanuel Louis Henri Alexandre de Launay, comte] D'Anteaigues and [Joseph] Fauche [sic] [Fouche] and the reports of [Gillaume Alexandre] Troncon de [Du]Counaray and [Antoine-Claire] Thibidau [sic] [Thibaudeau]; gives his opinion of the future French treatment of the U.S.
        - [John Marshall], Paris, [France], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 27 November 1797., 3 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:5)
          Has received no letters from her nor from his friends in the U.S.; will not be home until May and hopes that the Randolph's Executors case can be postponed until then; mentions amusements and dissipations of Paris; describes his new living arrangements [with Madame de Villette].
      - Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, J[ohn] Marshall, E[lbridge] Gerry, Paris, [France] to [Fulwar Stipwith, n.p.], 13 March [17]98., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Cannot settle or pay the accounts of American Consuls until the Congress of the United States acts on the matter; the three have agreed to transcend their powers to a limited extent in order to liberate distressed American seamen and return them to the U.S.
        Including TCy of ALS. 1 page.
        Original is privately owned.
      - Th[omas] Jefferson, [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], to General [John] Marshall, Oellers' hotel, [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 23 June [17]98., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Presents his compliments to Marshall; called at his lodgings twice this morning, but he [John Marshall] was not in; regrets that he will not be able to dine with him due to a previous engagement.
        Original is located in the Collection of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, on deposit at
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to "Polly" [Mary Willis Ambler) Marshall], Frederick [County, Virginia], 18 August [17]98., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Arrived in Richmond a week ago but hasn't been able to attend to his business because of his many callers and because of the heat; he enjoys the company of his three year old daughter, Mary; discusses the health of his son, John, who is cutting teeth.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond,, [Virginia], to Elbridge Gerry, n.p., 12 November [17]98., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Discusses Gerry's letter of 20 October 1798 to President John Adams, in which he [Elbridge Gerry] makes several misstatements about his part in the XYZ Affair, which Marshall now refutes point by point; "I must hope sir that you will think justly on this subject & will thereby save us both the pain of an altercation..."
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to George Washington, n.p., 1 May [17]99., 2 pages. Tcy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Apologizes for an article lately published listing the offices which he [George Washington] offered to him [John Marshall], with which he [John Marshall] had nothing to do; the writer of the article, who obtained no information directly or indirectly from him [John Marshall], "was unquestionably actuated by a wish to serve me and by resentment at the various malignant calumnies that have been so profusely bestowed on me."
        Original in the Washington Papers,
      - G[eorge] Washington, Mount Vernon, [Fairfax County, Virginia], to General [John] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], 5 May 1799., 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Is pleased with his [John Marshall's] election to the [Congress] even though by a small majority; discusses the elections; asks him to inform him of the election results when all are known.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [George Washington, n.p.], 16 May 1799., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Will communicate the enclosures of his [George Washington's] last letter to Col. [Edward] Carrington and Col. [William] Heth when they arrive in town; comments upon the elections and the unexpected defeat of Col. [George] Hancock and Major [?] Haywood; discusses the composition of the new state legislature; and upon France's declaration of war upon Austria and its consequences.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [George Washington, n.p.], 12 June [17]99., 4 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Discusses military appointments and recommends several officers, including Col. [John] Cropper, Genl. [George Rogers] Clark, Genl. [Thomas] Posey, Col. James Breckenbridge, Col. [Callohill] Minnis, Genl. [Robert] Porterfield of Augusta, Genl. [Joseph] Blackwell of Fauquier, and Col. [Joseph] Swearingean of Berkley; comments upon the death of Mr. [Patrick] Henry.
        Original is located in the Washington Papers,
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [George Washington, n.p.], 21 June [17]99., 1 page. Tcy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Was unable to return the enclosed letter because he was out of town and his happy that he [George Washington] is not displeased that it was not transmitted to Col. [John] Cropper; has just received his [George Washington's] second letter to that gentleman and will forward it immediately.
      - Indenture signed by Thomas Lord Fairfax leasing lands in the Manor of Leeds in Fauquier County, Virginia to Jesse Norman, 1 November 1799[?]., 1 page. Pst of ADS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Including Pst of ADS, 2 pages. 5 August 1812. Indenture of Isaac Arnold and Elija Arnold assigning the title of the Manor of Leeds to James K. Marshall.
        John Marshall House, Richmond, Virginia.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to James M[arkham] Marshall, Winchester, Virginia, 16 December [17]99., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Encloses a blank power of attorney in order to transfer and draw dividends upon his Pennsylvania Bank Stock which Mr. [?] Pleasant has just remitted him [John Marshall]; discusses land sales and the Manor of Leeds; discusses political situation and how the next election will affect their affairs; comments upon domestic unrest in regards to foreign affairs: " I look forward with more apprehension than I have ever done to the future political events of our country;" has just been informed of the total English defeat in Holland.
        Including TCy of ALS. 2 pages.
        Original is located in
        Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to John Ambler, near Williamsburg, Virginia, 29 December [17]99., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Congratulates him on his marriage; the newspapers report Philadelphia mourning the death of Genl. Washington; hopes that moderation and toleration will succeed the violence of the last session of Congress; party strife exasperates Pennsylvania; the Governor has threatened to turn out of office every man who voted against him.
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1800-1809., 28 items. (Box-folder 2:1-3)
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1800., 12 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Phila[delphia, Pennsylvania], to [James McDowall], n.p., 19 February 1800., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          Replies to a letter which proposed a change of the law for collecting the internal revenue of the U.S. in nonintercourse law with France; mentions that popular feeling is against it, as the public sees it responsible for present low price of tobacco.
        - J[ohn] Marshall[Washington, D.C.] to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 8 August 1800., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          Has received her letter of August 5 and is pleased with her account of the children's behavior; approves of her sending the boys "upcountry;" Tom's [Thomas Marshall] last letter contained no news of her health.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 20 August [1800]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          Has just returned from a visit to Mt. Vernon where the widowed Mrs. Washington appeared "tolerably cheerful;" hopes Polly would "show more firmness" as a widow; pleased with his young son, Jacqueline's, last letter and hopes his schooling with Mr. Burns will continue.
        - Indenture conveying John and Jane Foster's land in Hampshire County, Virginia [West Virginia] to John and James Marshall for $666.66, 10 November 1800., 3 pages. Pst of ADS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], to [Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, South Carolina?], 20 November 1800., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          Discusses the results of the presidential election of 1800 in Maryland, New England, and Pennsylvania, stating that it is "an absolute certainty that any success in your state [South Carolina] elects him [Thomas Jefferson].
          Original is located in the Pinckney Family Papers,
        - J[ohn] Marshall, [Washington, D.C.] to [?] [the commander of the 2nd Brig., Virginia militia], 25 November 1800., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          Reproaches himself for forgetting to recommend Major [?] Richardson to him [the commander of the 2nd Brig., Virginia militia] and does so now, hoping his neglect has not been a negative reflection of Richardson's abilities.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Department of State, [Washington, D.C.], to John Jay, Albany, New York, 28 November 1800., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          In compliance with his [John Jay] letter, the President [John Adams] has directed a requisition to be made to the Governor of Lower Canada for the delivery of Thomas Jamieson, alias Charles Splendor, a.k.a. Charles Johnston to the authorized person; the requisition and related documents are enclosed.
        - Secretary of State, J[ohn] Marshall, grants to Francis Didier Petit de Villers, agent for the ship Parlementaire Benjamin Franklin, a passport, 29 November 1800., 1 page. Pst. of DS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          Original is located in the Hampton L. Carson Collection,
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Department of State, [Washington, D.C.], to Rufus King, Lonoon, 4 December 1800., 4 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          Discusses the difficulties involved in the present negotiations between King and the British commissioners; the President [John Adams] informs him that an informal agreement will be satisfactory as it will be impossible to induce the British cabinet to abandon their principles; matters are left to his good judgment; the stipulation of a sum is better than the present unsettled situation.
          Original is located in the William M. Elkins Collection,
        - Tobias Lear, Walnut Tree Farm, [Virginia?], to General [John] Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], 12 December l800., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          His financial embarrassments have prevented him from devoting time to writing the history or General Washington's life; sends him [John Marshall] a trunk containing Washington's books and papers, and an enclosed list thereof; wishes he weren't so ignorant of bankruptcy proceedings.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to [Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, South Carolina ?], 18 December 1800., 3 pages. Pst or ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          Presidential candidates, [Thomas] Jefferson and [Aaron] Burr, have an equal number or votes, and thus the House or Representatives must decide the issue; Marshall aces not care which way the election goes, but "witnesses the anxiety of parties;" suspects the contest will be decided by South Carolina; even it Jefferson wins, Burr probably "will not surrender...all his pretensions to the office;" is chagrined by the late Federalist defeat and blames unfaithful men like Mr. [Marston?] or Rhode Island who threw away their votes, as attributed in the letters to General [Alexander] Hamilton's pamphlet; the treaty with France is before the Senate; Chief Justice [Oliver] Ellsworth has resigned and Mr. [John] Jay has been nominated in his place; looks forward to returning to Richmond in March and leaving behind forever his political career.
          Original is located in the Pinkney Family Papers,
          Library of Congress, Washington D.C.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Department of State, [Washington, D.C.], to Henry Vanderburgh, n.p. 29 December 1800., 1 page. Pst or DS. (Box-folder 2:1)
          An expression of the sentiments or respect which accompanied Vanderburgh's presidential commission to become a judge of Indiana Territory.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to Rufus King, London, 26 February 1801., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Discusses the probable policies of the new [Jefferson] administration; they will strengthen the state governments at the expense of the Federal, transferring as many powers to the House of Representatives as possible; the cabinet will probably consist of [James] Madison as Secretary of State, [Henry] Dearbourne[sic] as Secretary of War, [Albert] Gellatin or [Abraham] Baldwin as Secretary of the Treasury, maybe General [Robert] Smith as Secretary of the Navy, and [Levi] Lincoln or Mr. Livingstone [Robert R. Livingston] as Attorney General; many of Jefferson's party are disposed to press on to war, but the government will probably excite as much hate and resentment as possible amongst the people against England without proceeding to actual hostilities; the ill conduct of the British cruisers and Vice Admiralty and the remonstrances of American merchants well serves this purpose; delay the completion of your mission until you hear from the new administration as the present agreement with the British would not be ratified.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to Thomas Jefferson, [Washington, D.C.], 2 March 1801., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Accepts his [Thomas Jefferson's] offer to administer the Presidential oath of office to him.
        Original is located in the Jefferson Papers,